# **Deniz Berfin KARAKOC**

Illinois, USA 61801

karakoc2@illinois.edu

denizberfinkarakoc.github.io

+1 541-908-0137

## **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

# **Scientific Methods**

## **Application Areas**

- Network science
- Optimization
- Food trade networks
- Transportation systems

- Multi-criteria decision-making
- Data analytics
- Interdependent infrastructures

- Geographic information science
  - **Econometrics**

My research vision is addressing the 21st century challenges against resilient, equitable, and sustainable cyber-physicalsocial systems. I am especially interested in enhancing the multi-dimensional resilience of agri-food trade networks, transportation systems, and interdependent infrastructures. Please see my Google Scholar page for more details.

EDUCATION	
Aug 2019 – Present (May 2024 exp. grad.)	Ph.D., Civil and Environmental Engineering Sustainable and Resilient Infrastructure Systems
	University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, Illinois USA
	Thesis: Resilience of food flow networks across spatial scales CGPA: 3.95/4.00
Aug 2017 – May 2019	M.S., Industrial and Systems Engineering
	University of Oklahoma, Norman, Oklahoma USA
	Thesis: Community vulnerability perspectives on infrastructure
	network resilience decision-making CGPA: 4.00/4.00
Aug 2017 – May 2019	Grad.Cert, Geographic Information Science
	University of Oklahoma, Norman, Oklahoma USA
	CGPA: 4.00/4.00
Sept 2012 – July 2016	<b>B.S., Industrial Engineering</b> Bilkent University, Ankara, TURKEY Senior Project: Hot Sales Delivery System Logistics Optimization and Cost Analysis CGPA: 3.19/4.00

#### EXPERIENCE

EAI ERIEICE		
Aug 2019 - Present	Graduate Research Assistant, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign	
Aug 2017 – May 2019	Graduate Research Assistant, University of Oklahoma	
Aug 2017 – May 2019	Graduate Teaching Assistant, University of Oklahoma ISE 3293/5013 - Fundamentals of Engineering Statistical Analysis ISE 3293/5013 - Applied Engineering Statistics ISE 4553/5553 - Data-Driven Decision Making I	
Jan 2015 – June 2015	Undergraduate Teaching Assistant, Bilkent University IE 375 - Production Planning	

#### **AWARDS and HONORS**

Nature Food Cover Theme – Volume 4 Issue 7, July 2023

Structural chokepoints determine the resilience of agri-food supply chains in the United States

**Dissertation Completion Fellowship** – University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Graduate College, 2023-2024 *The only awarded senior Ph.D. candidate from the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering* 

CEE Rising Stars (invitee) - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2023

**Best Thesis Award** - University of Oklahoma School of Industrial and Systems Engineering, 2019 *The only awarded senior M.S. student from the School of Industrial and Systems Engineering* 

**14<sup>th</sup> Industrial Engineering Senior Design Project Contest and Fair Winner** - Bilkent University, 2016 *The only awarded B.S. senior design project from the Department of Industrial Engineering* 

Undergraduate Operations Research Prize Finalist - INFORMS Annual Meeting, 2016

Mavis Future Faculty Fellowship – University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign College of Engineering, 2023-2024

ACDIS Summer Fellowship – University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign College of Liberal Arts & Sciences, 2023

Future BAProf (invitee) – University of Iowa Tippie College of Business, 2023

WiNS Collabathon (invitee) - Women in Network Science (WiNS) Society, 2023

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

## Peer-reviewed Journal Articles (published)

- 1. Karakoc, D.B., Konar, M., Puma, M.J., Varshney, L.V. 2023. <u>Structural chokepoints determine the resilience of agri-food supply chains in the United States</u>, *Nature Food*, 4: 607–615. (**Impact Factor: 20.974**) (<u>Nature Food July 2023 Cover</u>)
- 2. Pandit, A., Karakoc D. B., Konar M. 2023. <u>Spatially detailed agricultural and food trade between China and the United States</u>, *Environmental Research Letters*, 18: 084031. (**Impact Factor: 6.947**)
- 3. Karakoc, D. B., Barker K. and González A. 2023. <u>Analyzing the tradeoff between vulnerability and recoverability investments for interdependent infrastructure networks</u>, *Socio-Economic Planning Sciences*, 87: 101508. (Impact Factor: 4.641)
- **4.** Maraqa, S. N., **Karakoc D. B.,** Ghorbani-Renani N., Barker K. and González A. 2022. <u>Project schedule compression for the efficient restoration of interdependent infrastructure systems</u>, *Computers & Industrial Engineering*, 170: 108342. (**Impact Factor: 7.18**)
- **5.** Wang, J. **Karakoc D. B.**, Konar M. 2022. <u>The Carbon Footprint of Cold Chain Food Flows in the United States</u>, *Environmental Research: Infrastructure and Sustainability*, 2: 021002.
- **6. Karakoc, D. B.,** Wang J., Konar M. 2022. <u>Food flows between counties in the United States from 2007 to 2017,</u> *Environmental Research Letters,* 17: 034035. (**Impact Factor: 6.947**)
- 7. Karakoc, D. B., Konar M. 2021. <u>A Complex Network Framework for the Efficiency and Resilience Trade-off in Global Food Trade</u>, *Environmental Research Letters*, 16: 105003. (Impact Factor: 6.947)
- 8. Karakoc, D. B., Barker K., Zobel C. and Almoghathawi Y. 2020. <u>Social-Vulnerability and Equity Perspectives on Interdependent Infrastructure Network Component Importance</u>, *Sustainable Cities and Society*, 57: 102072. (Impact Factor: 10.969)

9. Karakoc, D. B., Almoghathawi Y., Barker K., González A. and Mohebbi S. 2019. Community-Resilience Driven Restoration Model for Interdependent Infrastructure Networks, International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction, 38: 101228. (Impact Factor: 4.842)

## **Peer-reviewed Conference Articles (published)**

- 1. Karakoc, D. B., Barker K. and Almoghathawi Y. 2019. <u>Interdependent Infrastructure Network Restoration Optimization Problem from Community and Spatial Resilience Perspective</u>, In INOC 2019 *Proceedings of International Network Optimization Conference*, Avignon, France.
- 2. Barker, K., Karakoc D.B. and Almoghathawi Y. 2018. <u>Interdependent Infrastructure Network Restoration Problem from Community-Resilience Perspective</u>, In ESREL 2018 *Proceedings of European Safety and Reliability Conference, Trondheim, Norway*.

## Peer-reviewed Journal Articles (submitted and in preparation)

- **1. Karakoc, D. B.**, Konar M. 2023. Mapping food flows on critical transportation infrastructure in the United States. In progress. Targeted to: *Nature Food*.
- **2. Karakoc, D. B.**, Konar M. 2023. Optimization of national grain imports to balance risk and return: A portfolio theory approach. Submitted to: *Environmental Research Letters*.

## **ACADEMIC SERVICES**

## **Leadership Services**

- Presentation Judge, Undergraduate Research Symposium, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, 2023
- Session Chair, Empirical analysis for food supply chain decision-making, INFORMS Annual Meeting, 2023
- Session Convener, Affordable, sustainable, and resilient food supply chains, AGU Fall Meeting, 2023

## **Mentorship Services**

Mentor, WiNS Mentorship Program, Women in Network Science Society, 2023

#### **Outreach Services**

- Data production and preparation, "Food flows between U.S. counties in 2007, 2012, and 2017", foodflows.org
- K-12 instructor, "Resilient food supply chains", CEE Summer Camp 2023, wyse.engineering.illinois.edu
- Blog post preparation, "Mapping Food Flow Networks and the Food Supply Chain", farmdocdaily.illinois.edu

#### **Peer-review Services**

Journal of Industrial Ecology (2023), Nature Food (2022-2023), Nature Scientific Reports (2022), Food Policy (2022), Water Resources Research (2021), Economic System Research (2020), PLoS ONE (2020)

## **SELECTED PRESENTATIONS**

## **Conference Talks**

- 1. Carbon footprint of cold-chain food flows between counties in the United States, Production and Operations Management Society, **POMS Annual Conference 2023**.
- 2. Food flows between U.S. counties through time, The American Geophysical Union, AGU Fall Meeting 2021.
- 3. Resilience and efficiency in food trade networks, The American Geophysical Union, AGU Fall Meeting 2020.
- 4. Community-resilience driven trade-off analysis between the pre- and post-event investments for interdependent infrastructure networks, Institute of Industrial and Systems Engineers, IISE Annual Conference & Expo 2019.
- **5.** A social-vulnerability driven component importance measure for interdependent infrastructure networks, The Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences, **INFORMS Annual Meeting 2018.**

- **6.** Interdependent Infrastructure Network Restoration Problem from Multiple Community-Resilience Approaches, Institute of Industrial and Systems Engineers, **IISE Annual Conference & Expo 2018**.
- 7. Hot Sales Delivery System Logistics Optimization and Cost Analysis, The Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences, **INFORMS Annual Meeting 2016**.

#### **Invited Talks**

- 1. Community resilience perspective on interdependent infrastructure network restoration planning and component importance analysis, Disaster Resilience Analytics Center Seminar Series, 2022, Wichita State University.
- 2. Food supply chain bottlenecks, 2022, The MITRE Corporation.
- 3. Network analysis of food supply chains, Sustainability & Resistant Infrastructure Systems Seminar Series, 2021, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign.

## **CERTIFICATES and SKILLS**

Workshop Certificates Challenging Racism in Service Learning Integrating an Anti-Racist Approach, 2023

Peer Review Excellence: IOP Training and Certification, 2021

Technical Skills Python, MATLAB, R Studio, Minitab, ANOVA, Gurobi Optimization, FICO Xpress

Optimization, GAMS, Julia Optimization, ArcGIS, QGIS, WindPRO, MapInfo, LaTeX

#### MEDIA COVERAGE

American Council on Science and Health: "From Farm to Fork: Our Food Supply Chain", by Chuck Dinerstein, 01 August 2023. https://www.acsh.org/news/

New Food Magazine: "How resilient are US food supply chains?" by Grace Galler, 24 July 2023.

https://www.newfoodmagazine.com/news/

Nature Food: "**Logistics hubs hold food supply chains together**", News & Views by Graham K. MacDonald, 20 July 2023. https://www.nature.com/articles/

News: "Researchers illuminate resilience of U.S. supply chains" by UIUC Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, 20 July 2023. https://cee.illinois.edu/news/

## **REFERENCES**

## Dr. Megan Konar (Ph.D. Advisor)

Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

E-mail: mkonar@illinois.edu

## Dr. Kash Barker (M.S. Advisor)

School of Industrial and Systems Engineering University of Oklahoma

E-mail: kashbarker@ou.edu

#### Dr. Lei Zhao (Ph.D. Committee Member)

Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

E-mail: leizhao@illinois.edu

Dr. Michael Puma (Ph.D. Committee Member)

Center for Climate Systems Research

Columbia University

E-mail: mjp38@columbia.edu

## Dr. Lav Varshney (Ph.D. Committee Member)

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

E-mail: varshney@illinois.edu